# VICTOR UGHONU

Software Engineer (FullStack)

<u>linkedin.com/in/victor-ughonu</u> <u>www.miravicson.com</u> <u>github.com/Miravicson</u> <u>victorughonu@gmail.com</u>

## **PROFILE**

For over half a decade, I have groomed my technical expertise while providing value for several companies. I have worked in a fast-paced fintech startup as a champion for the application of Internal tools; I have worked in a travel agency company to build intuitive applications to help users plan their itineraries. I took my part in aiding businesses to drive up their customers by managing and maintaining a backend application for a company that runs a campaign management solution. In all these companies, I worked as a Full-stack developer developing the APIs and User Interfaces using TypeScript/JavaScript, React, NodeJs, and GraphQL and associated technologies.

#### **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

### \* Software Developer (FullStack), Dot.ai

January, 2023 — Present Netherland, (Remote)

- Implemented a Koa Node. Js Service that exposed APIs for querying and aggregating financial transaction information from Elastic Search using the Elastic search query API.
- Contributed to setup a data replicator instance on AWS RDS that migrates Data from PostgreSQL database to Elastic Search
- Implemented caching using Redis to speed up query for aggregated financial transaction information from Elastic Search resulting in a 3x improve
  in response time.
- Integrated A React and Redux Dashboard with the optimized Elastic Search-powered API while using React Query as the Ajax client and Redux Tool Kit as state management library.
- Built custom React hooks for fetching server data using React Query hooks and Axios library.
- Designed and Led the development of a Retail application for selling Health Insurance packages.
- Implemented the Frontend Application for the Retail application with NextJs 13, Redux Toolkit, TypeScript React Query, TailwindCss and CSS Modules.
- Improved website component accessibility by customizing HeadlessUI accessible component for common components like Menu, Dialog, Modal, Dropdown, and Switch.
- Implemented a Design system for the retail website component to improve component documentation and visibility thereby improving developer experience.
- Converted the Retail Website Design system on Figma into a TailwindCss design system thereby ensuring that all the components implemented pixel-perfect and design compliant.
- Setup a Koa.Js, Node.Js backend service written in TypeScript and powered by PostgreSQL database accessed through Prisma ORM.
- Designed an Insurance purchase/subscription database schema on DB diagrams and converted it into a Prisma DB Schema.
- Implemented APIs to allow Registration and Purchase of Insurance plans.
- Implemented third-party Integration with PayStack that allowed customers to pay for plans and with a third-party CBA for enrolling customers that have paid into the insurance plan.
- Implemented reusable request-validation middleware that utilized class-transformer and class-validator typescript libraries to validate API input in a declarative manner. This led to improved security and improved developer experience by eliminating boiler-plate code.
- Modelled PostgreSQL database relationship and tables for the Issue/ticket management system.
- Maintained CI/CD pipeline that runs and test application using ArgoCD, Docker, Docker-Compose and deploys that service to AWS.

# \* Software Developer (FullStack), Turing.com

February, 2022 — October, 2022 California, USA (Remote)

- Built automated unit test and contract test suites for the company core communications and email application using Node.js, Mocha and Chai.
   Reviewed and validated the development of new features to ensure the API design and underlying logic remained consistent.
- Grew customer retention by 70% by implementing Nest.Js- Node.Js (TypeScript) API that enabled developers update their Job availability.
- Integrated WhatsApp API to a Nest.Js service and wrote logic that captured WhatsApp messages and save them in a MySQL database.
- Took part in migrating plain MySQL queries in a NodeJs service to a TyperORM managed query.
- Collaborated with fellow backend engineers in migrating a JavaScript NodeJs service to TypeScript.
- Engineered email domain-warmup algorithm to improve email domain reputation leading to a reduction of spam rate by 50% and the increment of emails sent by 200%.
- Implemented an algorithm that progressively increased the number of emails sent through a newly registered domain geometrically across a set time period (Domain warmup) by leveraging Redis and CronJobs.
- Coordinated sprint planning, created and assigned tickets from feature requirements.
- Enhanced visibility into email performance by 50% through the integration of an experimentation framework that measures and records metrics across different email channels used to communicate with customers.
- Implemented Role Base Access using a Node. Js service and a React. Js application for the company's communication application. I utilized Redux
  Toolkit and Redux for application statement management and used Axios and React Query for client-server Ajax communication and Server state
  management on the frontend.
- Implemented monitoring API for generation of metrics using Prometheus and also integrated generated metrics to Grafana for visualization.

### \* Software Developer (Backend) Contract, Growsurf.com

March, 2022 — August, 2022 Chicago, USA (Remote)

- Enhanced code quality, reduced API latency and reduced bugs caused by resource starvation by migrating about 10% of cron jobs from a monolith JavaScript API codebase to micro service written in TypeScript.
- Utilized NATS streaming to communicate across a NestJs, Node.js microservice.
- Maintained and built features on a NestJs Node. Js Micro service monorepo that used MongoDB as Database, Mongoose as ORM, Redis for
  caching, Datadog for log monitoring, Docker, Kubernetes as part of the deployment pipeline and Hosted on Google Cloud Platform (GCP).
- Refined the campaign participant CSV export process by re-engineering the API-Client communication from a synchronous request-response
  system to an asynchronous job-based flow that leveraged various micro services, consequently achieving a 300% increase in the number of exported
  data.
- Empowered customer operations team by creating an internal tool application that enabled the team to perform administrative functions by themselves, eliminating developer distractions and enhancing developer productivity by 10%.
- Managed and refined several Cron Jobs that performed code administrative task like resolving invalid Campaign state, retrying certain failed async
  processes, computing aggregate information and generating reports.

# \* Software Developer (FullStack), Nomba.com (Formerly Kudi.com)

March, 2019 — February, 2022

Lekki, Lagos

- Engineered an accounting feature that lets customers and customer operations team export account statement, transaction history and balance of customers in different media formats leading to a 5% improvement in process visibility and saving the company \$50000 loss to fraudsters.
- Collaborated with UI/UX Designer to build an In-house React/Node Js dashboard to enable colleagues monitor and reconcile transactions, resolve
  transaction-related issues from the mobile application and reconcile transaction statements from financial partners. Reduced the time taken to
  resolve and reconcile transactions from a week to 3 seconds
- Liased with the Data team to switch the backing service for the Internal dashboard from Bigquery to ElasticSearch while ensuring the API response remained consistent and consequently preventing the client app from breaking. Reduced cost of query by 70% and decreased latency to maximum of 3 seconds
- Increased transaction count by 20% by implementing float management algorithm that intelligently funnels funds from source accounts to destination accounts where they are used to service customer transactions. This eliminated manual intervention and reduced charge-back by 15%.
- Developed a NodeJs service for automatically resolving transactions less than 5000 Naira, thereby freeing the Customer success team of the burden
  of resolving about a five thousand transactions per day
- Maintained 5+ microservice as code owner and reviewed over 200+ pull request.

### \* Midlevel Software Engineer (FullStack), Nomba.com (Formerly Kudi.com)

March, 2019 — February, 2022

Lekki, Lagos

- · Built a billing feature on a Node Js Service that enabled customers pay for electricity bill, Tv license, Internet, and airtime.
- Implemented a Node.Js re-query API that queries partner services for a state of bill transaction and consequently resolves failed or stuck transactions.
- Maintained a Python Issue resolving script that contained functions used to reset invalid or stuck transactions to a valid state.
- Implemented a float Management Node. Js Express API with Typescript and a React. Js Redux Interface that enabled a permitted customer support
  personnel to set configurations parameters that determined how Incoming funds to the companies Source accounts is funnelled through to other
  destination accounts where they are used to support other companies processes. Redis was used to store and query the configurations and also to
  manage a CronJob that ultimately moved the money.
- Implemented a transaction log Node. Js API that was responsible for storing and retrieving transaction logs of all funds moved from source accounts
  to destination accounts.
- Implemented a Node. Js API and a React Interface to enable permitted customer support personnel export transaction logs, Amount in either source account or destination account, pause the transfer of money and restart the transfer of funds.

# \* Junior Software Engineer (FullStack), Nomba.com (Formerly Kudi.com)

March, 2019 — February, 2022

Lekki, Lagos

- Built a React.Js Internal dashboard and a Node.Js Express API that migrated administrative and transaction monitoring features from a flailing jQuery dashboard. Supporting technology used in the project include, React Router, Redux, Scss/Sass, BigQuery, MongoDB.
- Wrote SQL queries to compute customers transaction statement for a given time range from Google BigQuery, implemented Node.Js service that utilised PDFKit to convert transaction statement result into a PDF that gets uploaded to Google Cloud Storage and also sent to user Email via SendGrid.
- Maintained a Python Flask application used to reconcile transactions statements from banking partners.
- Laid the code foundations for the middleware service that integrated the company's Core Business Application Microservices.

# \* Software Developer (FullStack), Orb Digital

May, 2020 — August, 2020

Lekki, Lagos

- Migrated the E-commerce react application from Firebase to proper NodeJs backend thereby reducing IaaS cost by 70%.
- Maintained and developed both Client React application and NodeJs Service increase test coverage by 10% and reducing the number of identified bugs by 80%.
- Prepared a software requirement document and groomed tickets based off the document leading to a 10% in lead time and 20% increase in number of tickets closed by teammates.

# \* Community Manager and Artificial Intelligence Innovator, Intel Corporation

November, 2015 — December, 2020

- Trained 107 Students on Artificial Intelligence deep learning and computer vision using the Intel Movidius Neural Compute Stick
- Secured \$1000 grant from Intel to organize programs to teach Artificial Intelligence
- Published a research on SpeakAI, an automation project built with Speech-To-Text technology
- Built a Django and Flask Application to utilized Speech-To-Text Model for Speech-To-Text translation.

## **EDUCATION**

## \* Obafemi Awolowo University

March, 2013 — April, 2018

Ile-Ife, Osun

 ${\it B.Sc. Electronic and Electrical Engineering}$ 

Subject Major: Control System Engineering and Intelligent Control, Solid-State Electronics

### Volunteering/Organizations:

- Intel Student Ambassador (2015) -- Organized technical community events on IoT and Cross-platform mobile application development
- ILab Robotics Group (2014) -- Participated in Nigerian Robotics Olympiad.

	PROGRAMMIN	G LANGUAGES	
	т	T. 0 :	T
JavaScript	Expert	TypeScript	Expert D. Ciricus
Python	Expert	Java ·····	Proficient
	CORE FRA	MEWORKS	
NodeJs	Expert	ReactJs	Expert
NestJs	Expert	NextJs	Expert
ExpressJs	Expert	Redux & Redux Toolkit	Proficient
ReactQuery	Proficient	Flask	Proficient
Django	Proficient		
	DATABASE AND	QUERY TOOLS	
M DD	<b>n</b>	M	<b>7</b> 1
MongoDB	Expert	Mongoose	Expert D. C
PostgreSQL	Proficient	Prisma	Proficient
MySQL	Proficient	SQLAlchemy	Proficient
Firebase	Proficient	Redis	Proficient
Google BigQuery	Proficient	Google CloudSQL	Proficient
GraphQL	Proficient	Google PubSub and Kakfa	Proficient
	DEPLOYMENT TOOLS	AND ENVIRONMENT	
Docker	Proficient	Github Actions	Proficient
AWS Cloud	Proficient	Heroku	Proficient
Google Cloud	Proficient	Digital Ocean and VPS Hosting	Proficient
Kubernetes	Proficient	0	<b>y</b>
CSS FRAMEWORKS AND TOOLS			
TailwindCSS	Expert	Ant Design	Proficient
Elastic UI	Proficient	Material UI	Proficient
SASS/SCSS	Expert	Styled Components	Proficient
	TESTING FR	<u>AMEWORKS</u>	
Mock Service Worker (MSW)	Proficient	React Testing Library	Proficient
Jest & Mocha	Proficient  Proficient	Spock Testing Framework and Groovy	Proficient
Jest et 1910ena	Projuieni	opock resulig transcook and Gloovy	Frojuteni
SOFT SKILLS			

# SOFT SKILLS

- $\bullet \quad \text{Knowledgeable in Continuous Integration and Continuous Deployment (CI/CD)}.$
- Knowledgeable in Microservice architecture and design.
- Knowledge of Data Structure and Algorithms.
- Experienced in remote working and collaboration.
- Knowledgeable in design and implementation of Event-Driven Systems.
- $\bullet \quad \text{In-depth knowledge of Scrum and agile software development.} \\$
- Ability to drive a project from whiteboard to production.